<metadata>
	<dataqual>
		<lineage>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Consolidated Data Basin Info: The members of the PA CAT team provided the latest protected areas data from their agencies in shapefile format. Protected areas from other agencies not represented within the PA CAT were procured directly from the managing entities or from older protected areas files. The shapefiles were compared within ArcMap to find duplicated areas and discrepancies. Overlaps and possible errors were analyzed and discussed within the team and consulted with other agency employees to determine how to proceed. We then edited the individual shapefiles to correct any errors found and simplify the attribute table. Using the Union tool in ArcGIS 3.2, we created a new shapefile with all the protected areas of Puerto Rico. The shapefile was then dissolved and the attribute table was edited to include GIS calculated areas.  
We found discrepancies between some adjacent protected areas that overlapped in places. In these situations we consulted the agencies that managed the protected areas. To eliminate overlaps we used the boundary of the protected area with either the most recent boundary or an official survey. The only case not resolved in this version is a small overlapping area between Finca Maria Luisa from Para la Naturaleza and Laguna Cartagena National Wildlife Refuge from the US Fish and Wildlife Service. Both areas appear to have official surveys. The team is working with both agencies to correct the data.</procdesc>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>ACRES</attrlabl>
				<attalias>ACRES</attalias>
				<attrdef>Area in Acres calculated in ArcGIS 3.2. Buffer zones show an area of 0 since they are not considered protected areas and therefore are not counted toward the total protected areas land for the country.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attalias>FID</attalias>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>GIS_SOURCE</attrlabl>
				<attalias>GIS_SOURCE</attalias>
				<attrdef>Original source of the GIS data for that protected area.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>HECTARES</attrlabl>
				<attalias>HECTARES</attalias>
				<attrdef>Area in hectares calculated using ArcGIS 3.2. Buffer zones show an area of 0 since they are not considered protected areas and therefore are not counted toward the total protected areas land for the country.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>LOC_DESIG</attrlabl>
				<attalias>LOC_DESIG</attalias>
				<attrdef>Name of the local designation. The local designation is assigned by the maneging agency and may not represent a cohesive system with consistent uses or regulations for similarly named designations.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>MGMT</attrlabl>
				<attalias>MGMT</attalias>
				<attrdef>Name of the agency or entity that manages de protected area.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
				<attalias>NAME</attalias>
				<attrdef>The name of the protected area</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>NOTES</attrlabl>
				<attalias>NOTES</attalias>
				<attrdef>Additional notes where needed.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>OWNERSHIP</attrlabl>
				<attalias>OWNERSHIP</attalias>
				<attrdef>Name of the agency or entity that owns the land. Some areas are owned by multiple agencies, entitites, private landowners or a combination thereof.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attalias>Shape</attalias>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>TERR_MAR</attrlabl>
				<attalias>TERR_MAR</attalias>
				<attrdef>This field informs wether the protected area is terrestrial or marine.</attrdef>
			</attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>YEAR_ESTAB</attrlabl>
				<attalias>YEAR_ESTAB</attalias>
				<attrdef>Year the protected area was established or acquired. In the case of Cavernas de Camuy this date represents when the park was first opened to the public. Many protected areas designation laws have been ammended to include new land or marine extensions.</attrdef>
			</attr>
		</detailed>
	</eainfo>
	<idinfo>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<sngdate>
					<caldate>1903-01-01T00:00:00 - 2016-12-23T00:00:00</caldate>
				</sngdate>
			</timeinfo>
		</timeperd>
		<useconst>The polygons in this file may not represent legal boundaries or may not be up to date. Protected areas are very dynamic and new areas are continually in the process of consideration, designation or delimitation. The boundaries represent the most recent information available as of December of 2016. Data set is not for use in litigation. While efforts have been made to ensure that these data are accurate and reliable within the state of the art, the agencies and entities involved, the CLCC, or the members of the PA-CAT, cannot assume liability for any damages, or misrepresentations, caused by any inaccuracies in the data, or as a result of the data to be used on a particular system. The team makes no warranty, expressed or implied, nor does the fact of distribution constitute such a warranty.</useconst>
		<descript>
			<abstract>This GIS file provides the latest compilation (as of the 23 of December of 2016) of the natural protected areas of Puerto Rico. Natural protected areas are geographic spaces clearly defined and delimited through legal or other effective means for the long-term conservation of their natural resources, biodiversity, ecosystem services and associated cultural values. This dataset includes all protected areas owned and managed or co-managed for the conservation of nature and natural resources by the following agencies and organizations: Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources (DNER), Para la Naturaleza, US Forest Service, US Fish and Wildlife Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), Fundación Casa Pueblo, Tropic Ventures Education and Research Foundation, Ciudadanos del Karso, University of Puerto Rico, Puerto Rico National Parks Program, Luis Muñoz Marin Foundation, and Instituto de Cultura Puertorriqueña. This version also includes the Karst Conservation Zone, an area of high ecological value with a strong legal foundation to protect the natural resources inside public and private lands within this zone. The protection and conservation of the Puerto Rico’s karstic area is mandated by Act 292 of August 21 of 1999, which commissions the identification of lands that should be restricted from commercial mining activities and other intensive uses. The restricted area was identified in DNER 2008 Karst Study and is also a DNER Priority Conservation Area, which prioritizes the acquisition of high ecological value land through mitigations, donations and land transfers from other government agencies. The Karst Conservation Zone included in this file is within the restricted area and represent lands zoned for conservation purposes within the Plan and Rules for the Karst Special Planning Area (PRAPEC) from 2013. Established land use rules explicitly prohibit mining and landfills within public and private lands, promote terrace cultivation and other sustainable agricultural practices as well as reforestation projects in order to protect and conserve the natural resources, water quality, and the delivery of ecosystem services within the karst restricted zone.The 2016 Protected Areas of Puerto Rico inventory includes the following updates:New from Para La Naturaleza:1. Área Natural Protegida Rio Bairoa2. Área Natural Protegida La Pitahaya3. Área Natural Protegida Los Llanos4. Área Natural Protegida Cerro La Tuna5. Área Natural Protegida Rio Toa Vaca6. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Lago7. Área Natural Protegida Freddie Ramírez8. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda PellejasNew from the Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources:9. Reserva Natural Playa Grande El Paraíso—DRNA10. Ext. Marina R.N. Playa Larga El Paraíso—DRNAUpdated boundariesPara La Naturaleza:1. Área Natural Protegida Medio Mundo y Daguao2. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Buena Vista—absorbs Marueño3. Área Natural Protegida Río Encantado4. Área Natural Protegida Cañón San CristóbalDepartment of Natural and Environmental Resources:5. Reserva Natural Planadas - Yeyesa—DRNA6. Finca Nolla—DRNAOverlap conflicts were identfied by the PACAT and reported to the agencies for revision. They are identified as overlap areas in this dataset and are not double counted. These are:1. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Pellejassmall overlap with Bosque del Pueblo de Adjuntas2. Planadas Yeyesasmall overlap with Piedras del ColladoChanges in the name or other attributes of existing protected areas:Servidumbre de Conservación Reserva Natural Punta Ballenas—Is part of multiple designations. Local designation changes to reflect this: Bosque Estatal / Reserva Natural / Servidumbre de Conservación (state forest, natural reserve, easement)Refugio de Vida Silvestre (RVS) Iris Alameda de Boquerón - B.E. de Boquerón—Is a natural reserve and part of the Boqueron State ForestReserva Natural Cayo Ratones - B. E. de Boquerón—Is a natural reserve and part of the Boqueron State ForestÁrea Natural Protegida Marueño—boundary change plus changes name to be part of Hacienda Buena VistaÁrea Natural Protegida Pedro Marrero name change to Área Natural Protegida Río Sana MuertoServidumbre de Conservación Don Ingenio name change to Área Natural Protegida Río Toro NegroGuayama Experimental Forest name change to Guayama Research AreaManati Experimental Forest name change to Manati Research AreaÁrea Natural Protegida Finca Jájome name change to Área Natural Protegida JájomeÁrea Natural Protegida Sendra name change to Área Natural Protegida Hermanas SendraFinca Los Frailes name change to Área Natural Protegida Los FrailesFinca Shapiro name change to Área Natural Protegida ShapiroÁrea Natural Protegida Río Toa Vaca name change to Área Natural Protegida Toa VacaThis version also includes fixes to small overlaps (slivers) between Seven Seas, Northeast Ecological Corridor, marine extent of the Northeast Ecological Corridor, and Cabezas de San Juan marine extent.The attribute table provides the following information about each protected area: name of the protected areas, management agency(s) or entity, land ownership, year established or acquired, local designation(s), whether the protected area is terrestrial or marine, GIS calculated area in hectares and acres, source of the data, and additional notes. The polygons in this file may not represent legal boundaries or may not be up to date. Protected areas are very dynamic, with new areas in the process of designation and/or delimitation. This file will be regularly updated as new protected areas emerge and old boundaries are updated. The boundaries represent the most recent information available as of December of 2016. This version of the protected areas shapefile was last updated on the 23 of December of 2016. This file is the product of a collaborative effort through the Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative (CLCC) Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA-CAT), which aims to compile, analyze and improve protected areas data for Puerto Rico and US Virgin Islands, identifying actions to improve the protected areas network and data sharing protocols of both countries. For more information please visit: &amp;lt;http://caribbeanlcc.org/&amp;gt; Suggested citation: Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative. 2016. Puerto Rico Protected Areas Database [version of December, 2016]. GIS data. San Juan, PR.</abstract>
			<purpose>Terrestrial and marine protected natural areas of Puerto Rico compiled by the Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative (CLCC) Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA CAT) as of December 2016. For more information please visit: http://caribbeanlcc.org/pacat. Suggested citation: Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative. 2016. Puerto Rico Protected Areas Database [version of December, 2016]. GIS data. San Juan, PR.</purpose>
		</descript>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntemail>kaseyrjacobs@caribbeanlcc.org mquinones@fs.fed.us soledad@paralanaturaleza.org cortiz@drna.gobierno.pr chechiasp@gmail.com marcela.canon@bahiabeachpuertorico.com</cntemail>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Protected Areas Conservation Action Team</cntper>
					<cntorg>Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<datacred>This file is the product of a collaborative effort through the Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative (CLCC), Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA CAT) For more information please visit:  Suggested citation: Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative. 2016. Puerto Rico Protected Areas Database [version of December, 2016]. GIS data. San Juan, PR.</datacred>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekey>protected areas,puerto rico,natural protected areas</themekey>
			</theme>
		</keywords>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<onlink>https://databasin.org/datasets/4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29</onlink>
				<title>Puerto Rico Natural Protected Areas (December 2016 Inventory)</title>
				<origin>Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative's Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA-CAT). Data from the Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources and Para La Naturaleza. The International Institute of Tropical Forestry GIS Lab compiled the information</origin>
				<origin>checked for PA-CAT quality control standards</origin>
				<origin>and combined the new data to the December 2015 inventory. Technicians from all three agencies as well as the Puerto Rico Planning Board identified the boundary changes</origin>
				<origin>name changes in the attribute table</origin>
				<origin>and other changes from the 2015 inventory as listed in the metadata.The
Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA-CAT) is composed of multiple partners</origin>
				<origin>including Federal and State agencies</origin>
				<origin>non-governmental organizations and
individuals from Puerto Rico and the United States Virgin Islands. These
include</origin>
				<origin>among others</origin>
				<origin>the Puerto Rico Department
of Natural and Environmental Resources (DNER)</origin>
				<origin>Virgin Islands Department of
Planning and Natural Resources (DPNR)</origin>
				<origin>International Institute of Tropical Forestry
(IITF) of the United States Forest Service (USFS)</origin>
				<origin>U.S. Fish and Wildlife
Service (USFWS)</origin>
				<origin>Puerto Rico Conservation Trust and its unit Para La Naturaleza</origin>
				<origin>Foundation Alma de Bahía</origin>
				<origin>Bahía Beach
Resort</origin>
				<origin>Puerto Rico Planning Board</origin>
				<origin>Foundation
for Development Planning</origin>
				<origin>Inc.</origin>
				<origin>University of the Virgin Islands</origin>
				<origin>and the
University of Puerto Rico. These agencies and organizations work together in an
alliance called the Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative.</origin>
				<othercit>Suggested citation: Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative. 2016. Puerto Rico Protected Areas Database [version of December, 2016]. GIS data. San Juan, PR.</othercit>
			</citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<southbc>2011315.9047</southbc>
				<northbc>2113288.3887</northbc>
				<eastbc>-7260106.7781</eastbc>
				<westbc>-7582668.084</westbc>
			</bounding>
		</spdom>
	</idinfo>
	<distinfo>
		<distliab>No warranty is made by Data Basin for use of this dataset.  No warranty is made by Data Basin regarding the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of this dataset. In no event shall Data Basin have any liability whatsoever for payment of any consequential, incidental, indirect, special, or tort damages of any kind, including, but not limited to, any loss of profits arising out of the use or reliance on the geographic or attribute data contained within this dataset or arising out of the delivery, installation, operation, or support by Data Basin.</distliab>
		<techpreq>Desktop GIS software.</techpreq>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtopt>
					<onlinopt>
						<accinstr>Download from https://databasin.org</accinstr>
						<computer>
							<networka>
								<networkr>https://databasin.org/datasets/4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29</networkr>
							</networka>
						</computer>
					</onlinopt>
				</digtopt>
				<digtinfo>
					<filedec>No compression applied</filedec>
					<formvern>ArcGIS 10</formvern>
					<formspec>Feature Layer</formspec>
					<formname>Feature Layer</formname>
				</digtinfo>
			</digform>
			<ordering>Download from https://databasin.org</ordering>
			<fees>None</fees>
		</stdorder>
		<distrib>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntvoice>541-757-0687</cntvoice>
				<cntemail>databasin_admin@consbio.org</cntemail>
				<cntperp>
					<cntorg>Data Basin</cntorg>
					<cntper>Data Basin Administrator</cntper>
				</cntperp>
				<cntaddr>
					<country>USA</country>
					<city>Corvallis</city>
					<postal>97333</postal>
					<address>136 SW Washington Ave, Suite 202</address>
					<addrtype>physical address</addrtype>
					<state>OR</state>
				</cntaddr>
			</cntinfo>
		</distrib>
	</distinfo>
	<Esri>
		<CreaDate>20161228</CreaDate>
		<CreaTime>21222000</CreaTime>
		<SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce>
		<DataProperties>
			<itemProps>
				<itemLocation>
					<linkage Sync="TRUE">file://C:\windows\temp\tmpgp8gyl\4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29\commondata\december2016_update\Areas_Protegidas_PR_Diciembre2016_CLCC_PACAT</linkage>
					<protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol>
				</itemLocation>
			</itemProps>
			<copyHistory>
				<copy source="C:\windows\temp\tmpgp8gyl\commondata\december2016_update\Areas_Protegidas_PR_Diciembre2016_CLCC_PACAT" dest="C:\windows\temp\tmpgp8gyl\4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29\commondata\december2016_update\Areas_Protegidas_PR_Diciembre2016_CLCC_PACAT" date="20161228" time="21222000"/>
			</copyHistory>
		</DataProperties>
	</Esri>
</metadata>
