<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<ESRI_ItemInformation Culture='en-US'>
<name>4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29</name>
<guid>411A818F-BC09-42AD-B377-6D1BD675291D</guid>
<catalogpath></catalogpath>
<snippet></snippet>
<description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This GIS file provides the latest compilation (as of the 23 of December of 2016) of the natural protected areas of Puerto Rico. Natural protected areas are geographic spaces clearly defined and delimited through legal or other effective means for the long-term conservation of their natural resources, biodiversity, ecosystem services and associated cultural values. This dataset includes all protected areas owned and managed or co-managed for the conservation of nature and natural resources by the following agencies and organizations: Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources (DNER), Para la Naturaleza, US Forest Service, US Fish and Wildlife Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), Fundación Casa Pueblo, Tropic Ventures Education and Research Foundation, Ciudadanos del Karso, University of Puerto Rico, Puerto Rico National Parks Program, Luis Muñoz Marin Foundation, and Instituto de Cultura Puertorriqueña. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This version also includes the Karst Conservation Zone, an area of high ecological value with a strong legal foundation to protect the natural resources inside public and private lands within this zone. The protection and conservation of the Puerto Rico’s karstic area is mandated by Act 292 of August 21 of 1999, which commissions the identification of lands that should be restricted from commercial mining activities and other intensive uses. The restricted area was identified in DNER 2008 Karst Study and is also a DNER Priority Conservation Area, which prioritizes the acquisition of high ecological value land through mitigations, donations and land transfers from other government agencies. The Karst Conservation Zone included in this file is within the restricted area and represent lands zoned for conservation purposes within the Plan and Rules for the Karst Special Planning Area (PRAPEC) from 2013. Established land use rules explicitly prohibit mining and landfills within public and private lands, promote terrace cultivation and other sustainable agricultural practices as well as reforestation projects in order to protect and conserve the natural resources, water quality, and the delivery of ecosystem services within the karst restricted zone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2016 Protected Areas of Puerto Rico inventory includes the following updates:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;New from Para La Naturaleza:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. Área Natural Protegida Rio Bairoa&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. Área Natural Protegida La Pitahaya&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;3. Área Natural Protegida Los Llanos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;4. Área Natural Protegida Cerro La Tuna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;5. Área Natural Protegida Rio Toa Vaca&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;6. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Lago&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;7. Área Natural Protegida Freddie Ramírez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;8. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Pellejas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;New from the Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;9. Reserva Natural Playa Grande El Paraíso—DRNA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;10. Ext. Marina R.N. Playa Larga El Paraíso—DRNA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Updated boundaries&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Para La Naturaleza:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. Área Natural Protegida Medio Mundo y Daguao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Buena Vista—absorbs Marueño&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;3. Área Natural Protegida Río Encantado&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;4. Área Natural Protegida Cañón San Cristóbal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department of Natural and Environmental Resources:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;5. Reserva Natural Planadas - Yeyesa—DRNA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;6. Finca Nolla—DRNA&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overlap conflicts were identfied by the PACAT and reported to the agencies for revision. They are identified as overlap areas in this dataset and are not double counted. These are:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. Área Natural Protegida Hacienda Pellejassmall overlap with Bosque del Pueblo de Adjuntas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. Planadas Yeyesasmall overlap with Piedras del Collado&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Changes in the name or other attributes of existing protected areas:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Servidumbre de Conservación Reserva Natural Punta Ballenas—Is part of multiple designations. Local designation changes to reflect this: Bosque Estatal / Reserva Natural / Servidumbre de Conservación (state forest, natural reserve, easement)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Refugio de Vida Silvestre (RVS) Iris Alameda de Boquerón - B.E. de Boquerón—Is a natural reserve and part of the Boqueron State Forest&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reserva Natural Cayo Ratones - B. E. de Boquerón—Is a natural reserve and part of the Boqueron State Forest&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Área Natural Protegida Marueño—boundary change plus changes name to be part of Hacienda Buena Vista&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Área Natural Protegida Pedro Marrero name change to Área Natural Protegida Río Sana Muerto&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Servidumbre de Conservación Don Ingenio name change to Área Natural Protegida Río Toro Negro&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guayama Experimental Forest name change to Guayama Research Area&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manati Experimental Forest name change to Manati Research Area&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Área Natural Protegida Finca Jájome name change to Área Natural Protegida Jájome&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Área Natural Protegida Sendra name change to Área Natural Protegida Hermanas Sendra&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finca Los Frailes name change to Área Natural Protegida Los Frailes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finca Shapiro name change to Área Natural Protegida Shapiro&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Área Natural Protegida Río Toa Vaca name change to Área Natural Protegida Toa Vaca&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This version also includes fixes to small overlaps (slivers) between Seven Seas, Northeast Ecological Corridor, marine extent of the Northeast Ecological Corridor, and Cabezas de San Juan marine extent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The attribute table provides the following information about each protected area: name of the protected areas, management agency(s) or entity, land ownership, year established or acquired, local designation(s), whether the protected area is terrestrial or marine, GIS calculated area in hectares and acres, source of the data, and additional notes. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The polygons in this file may not represent legal boundaries or may not be up to date. Protected areas are very dynamic, with new areas in the process of designation and/or delimitation. This file will be regularly updated as new protected areas emerge and old boundaries are updated. The boundaries represent the most recent information available as of December of 2016. This version of the protected areas shapefile was last updated on the 23 of December of 2016. This file is the product of a collaborative effort through the Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative (CLCC) Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA-CAT), which aims to compile, analyze and improve protected areas data for Puerto Rico and US Virgin Islands, identifying actions to improve the protected areas network and data sharing protocols of both countries. For more information please visit: &amp;lt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://caribbeanlcc.org/&quot;&gt;http://caribbeanlcc.org/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suggested citation: Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative. 2016. Puerto Rico Protected Areas Database [version of December, 2016]. GIS data. San Juan, PR.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

This dataset was uploaded to Data Basin and is available with additional information at: /datasets/4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29</description>
<summary></summary>
<title>4db5a86ee415471f94b46e0975a1ae29</title>
<tags></tags>
<type>Layer Package</type>
<typekeywords>
<typekeyword>Shapefile Feature Class</typekeyword>
<typekeyword>Layer Package</typekeyword>
<typekeyword>Data</typekeyword>
<typekeyword>ArcMap</typekeyword>
<typekeyword>ArcGlobe</typekeyword>
<typekeyword>ArcGIS Explorer</typekeyword>
<typekeyword>lpk</typekeyword>
</typekeywords>
<thumbnail>thumbnail/thumbnail.png</thumbnail>
<documentation></documentation>
<url></url>
<datalastmodifiedtime></datalastmodifiedtime>
<extent>
<xmin>-68.116265245144</xmin>
<ymin>17.7757425742186</ymin>
<xmax>-65.218646837119</xmax>
<ymax>18.6458857685896</ymax>
</extent>
<spatialreference>NAD_1983_StatePlane_Puerto_Rico_Virgin_Islands_FIPS_5200</spatialreference>
<accessinformation>Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative&apos;s Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA-CAT). &lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Data from the Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources and Para La Naturaleza. The International Institute of Tropical Forestry GIS Lab compiled the information, checked for PA-CAT quality control standards, and combined the new data to the December 2015 inventory. Technicians from all three agencies as well as the Puerto Rico Planning Board identified the boundary changes, name changes in the attribute table, and other changes from the 2015 inventory as listed in the metadata.&lt;div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The
Protected Areas Conservation Action Team (PA-CAT) is composed of multiple partners,
including Federal and State agencies, non-governmental organizations and
individuals from Puerto Rico and the United States Virgin Islands. These
include, among others,  the Puerto Rico Department
of Natural and Environmental Resources (DNER), Virgin Islands Department of
Planning and Natural Resources (DPNR),  International Institute of Tropical Forestry
(IITF) of the United States Forest Service (USFS), U.S. Fish and Wildlife
Service (USFWS), Puerto Rico Conservation Trust and its unit Para La Naturaleza,
 Foundation Alma de Bahía, Bahía Beach
Resort, Puerto Rico Planning Board, Foundation
for Development Planning, Inc., University of the Virgin Islands, and the
University of Puerto Rico. These agencies and organizations work together in an
alliance called the Caribbean Landscape Conservation Cooperative.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</accessinformation>
<licenseinfo></licenseinfo>
</ESRI_ItemInformation>
